Inventory of the Weldon E. Lewis, Jr. Papers 1943-1945
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Weldon E. Lewis, Jr. Papers 1943-1945 1943-1945
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2007.42
1.00
Lewis, Weldon E., Jr.; Lewis, Madge C. arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center on 00/00/2007.
Biographical Note
Weldon Eli Lewis, Jr. was the son of Weldon Eli Lewis and Zula Frances Henry Lewis. He was born October 16, 1910 in Hot Springs, Arkansas and died April 19, 1970, location unknown.He married Madge Colglazier on February 14, 1943.He was a Corporal in the U.S.Army, stationed at Camp Cooke, California, before becoming a Sergeant in mid-January 1943. By May 1943 he was stationed near Nashville, Tennessee and by December 1943 he was stationed near Indiantown Gap, Pennsylvania. By April 1944, he was stationed in England, France and possibly other European locations, until at least September 1945. Further information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki: http://scrc.swem.wm.edu/wiki/index.php/Weldon E. Lewis, Jr..
Scope and Contents
This is a collection of letters written mainly by Sgt. Weldon Eli Lewis, Jr. while he served in the 5th and 7th Army during World War II. He was in the Special Platoon of the company called Contact Platoon. The majority of the letters are written by Sgt. Weldon E. Lewis to his wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis. Some letters are written by Sgt. Lewis to his son, Weldon E. Lewis, III, his parents, Mr. and Mrs. Weldon E. Lewis and his in-laws, Mr. and Mrs. Carl M. Colglazier. A few letters were written by Madge Lewis and others to Sgt. Lewis after the war and were forwarded to his home after he returned. A few clippings and empty envelopes are included with the papers.Sgt. Lewis wrote about how he missed and loved his wife, about the good times they had, about his son who was born while he was in the army, about his and his wife's family, about the stress of being separated for so long and about the anticipation of his homecoming.The 1943 letters deal with their relationship and attempts to be together while he is stationed in the United States. The 1944 and 1945 letters show his sadness about missing his son's growth and his uncertainty about his relationship with his wife, plus comments on his wife's difficulties with his family and the war being hard on them all. Even though Sgt. Lewis never goes into detail about his military operations, and even comments that such writing could endanger the war effort, he does write about his military training, his maneuvers, his social life, his rations, his leaves to London and Paris, his tank named "For Manny", his stays in the hospital, his view of Germany, his shock about President Roosevelt's death, VE Day, combat and his opinions on the war. Not until May 1945 did he reveal what his unit and position were, where he had been during the war and how combat affected him.
Arrangement of Materials
Series I, Letters, is arranged by writer or recipient, then chronologically within each subseries. Series II, Printed Material, is arranged chronologically, though most items are undated. Series III contains empty envelopes.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence
Personal Name:
Lewis, Madge Calglazier; Lewis, Weldon E., Jr.
Topical Term:
World War, 1939-1945--European Front; World War, 1939-1945.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Letters, 1943-1945; id1900
  - Letters Written by Weldon E. Lewis, 1943-1945; id1903 (Sub-series 1)
    - id2146 (Sub-series 1, Box 1)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, 1943; id2134 (Sub-series 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, April 1944; id2136 (Sub-series 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, June - August 1944; id2137 (Sub-series 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, September - October 1944; id2138 (Sub-series 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, November 1944; id2139 (Sub-series 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, December 1944; id2140 (Sub-series 1, Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, January - February 1945; id2141 (Sub-series 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, March 1945; id2142 (Sub-series 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
    - id2150 (Sub-series 1, Box 2)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, April 1945; id2148 (Sub-series 1, Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, May 1945; id2149 (Sub-series 1, Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, June 1945; id2151 (Sub-series 1, Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, July 1945; id2152 (Sub-series 1, Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, August 1945; id2153 (Sub-series 1, Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Written to his Wife, Madge Colglazier Lewis, September 1945; id2154 (Sub-series 1, Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Written to Welden E. Lewis, III, 1944-1945; id2158 (Sub-series 1, Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Written to Parents and In-laws, 1944-1945; id2159 (Sub-series 1, Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Weldon E. Lewis, Jr., 1945; id2133 (Sub-series 2)
    - id2147 (Sub-series 2, Box 2)
      - Letters to Weldon E. Lewis, Jr. from his wife, Madge C. Lewis, August 30, 1945 - September 11, 1945; id2132 (Sub-series 2, Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Letter to Weldon E. Lewis, Jr. from Weldon E. Lewis, III (Manny), January 1945; id2131 (Sub-series 2, Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Letter to Weldon E. Lewis, Jr. from Aunt Molly Goldburg, September 11, 1945; id2130 (Sub-series 2, Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letter written to Madge and Manny (Weldon E. Lewis, III) Lewis, 1945; id2129 (Sub-series 3)
    - id54535 (Sub-series 3, Box 2)
      - Letter Written to Madge and Manny Lewis, September 12 probably 1945; id2155 (Sub-series 3, Box 2, Folder 12)
- News Clippings, id1901
  - id54536 (Box 2)
    - News Clippings, undated; id2157 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Empty Envelopes, 1943-1945; id1902
  - id54537 (Box 2)
    - Empty Envelopes, 1943-1945; id2156 (Box 2, Folder 14)